<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflexions upon the controversy about the oath of allegiance, occasion'd by the letter in answer to English loyalty</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58381</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825066</idno>
  <idno type="VID">29438</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248505430</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R728</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200418</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825066</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99825066e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58381)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29438)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2039:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflexions upon the controversy about the oath of allegiance, occasion'd by the letter in answer to English loyalty</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Jacob Tonson, at the Judges-Head, in Chancery-Lane; and James Vade, at the Cock and Sugar-Loaf, in Fleet-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Cropped at head affecting pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  Catholic Church --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Loyalty oaths --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29438:1"/>
            <p>REFLEXIONS UPON THE CONTROVERSY About the <hi>Oath of Allegiance,</hi> Occasion'd by the LETTER In ANSWER to English Loyalty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonson,</hi> at the <hi>Judges-Head,</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane;</hi> and <hi>James Vade,</hi> at the <hi>Cock</hi> and <hi>Sugar-Loaf,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-Street,</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:29438:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29438:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>'TIs a wise Preamble, and like to recommend what follows much, to confess at first, that <hi>I am going to Write,</hi> sounds even to my own Ears little better, than <hi>I am going to play the Fool.</hi> And yet what can one hope from scribling, in an Age, wherein if two Cart Load of Pamphlets could have made one Convert, we had been all of one mind in <hi>England</hi> before this. People will buy a Pamphlet, because it is cheap, and Read it because they have nothing else to do: But what they thought before, they will think still, let the Pamphlet say what it can. What I <hi>think</hi> true <hi>is</hi> true, is the Rule; and <hi>does he say as I say,</hi> as much the Touchstone of Truth, as <hi>does he like my Play,</hi> of Wit. Should Truth her self come among us, she would hazard her Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, unless she came Tongue-ty'd. He whom she contradicted, would go neer to take her for a Jilt. For all that, whether Fool, or no Fool, is as the <hi>Reader</hi> pleases. I need not wear yellow, if any body will be the wiser for what I Write. If every Body be Obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to make no profit by any Book, of all Mankind
<pb facs="tcp:29438:3"/>they spend their Time the worst, who learn to Read. Since at worst 'tis a Folly <hi>A-la-mode,</hi> I will trust the <hi>Readers</hi> good Nature for once, and be in at the <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance. 'Tis a game, as much as lyes upon it, in my Opinion ill play'd, whether the fault be in the Game or Gamesters. One may be fond of sport, more Sollicitous to play than win; or a Game may be cross, and which will be play'd no better. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be, at the rate it now goes, the Lookers-on are not like to know in hast what becomes of their Bets. My concern in them has made a Pamphlet of the thoughts, which much Reflection on man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> instances has produc't, and the Answerer of <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Reviv'd.</hi> I am far from meaning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him; but cannot avoid bringing my instan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> would have any thing mended, must need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and why I make bold with his, since I must <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> somebo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, because they are the most fresh and at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d, and the last puff still calls out the Flame. To do th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s will, in spite of my Teeth, look like an Answer to so much. But yet my business is with the Voucher, not the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary, and I shall give him cause to believe, I am not the merciless Enemy, call'd an Answerer, who spares nothing.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29438:3"/>
            <p>TO begin then: I wish those who write, would order it so, that some Body may be the better, besides the <hi>Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> For methinks an <hi>Author</hi> is, or should be something more, than barely an Implement to the <hi>Printing</hi>-Trade. Children were not set to School, with design to make no other Use of their Learning. I know not who is like to be the better, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cloy'd with the same Stories over and over again, not a jot mended in the telling, and but little vary'd, and which every Body knows as well as the Teller. I cannot but grieve to see, this is the Case of most Anti-Allegiance-Writings. The Briefs, and Councils are all you shall generally find any where. They are all the Substance of this Letter, save an Argument with never a true Proposition in it, about the word <hi>Treasons.</hi> Are these any Secrets? Have they not been urged, and canvast, and turn'd all manner of ways, almost these fourscore Years, all save the last, which is indeed, I think, of a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Invention, but no Secret neither. Yet after all, People think as they do; and can it be imagined, that who was not moved by hearing them Yesterday, shall, by hearing them to Day, it may be worse told? Indeed, he who will pretend, there has not been so much need of them as they will bear, and that he can make more, says something: But he who barely says them over again, either says nothing, or would have done better if he had.</p>
            <p>Again, has the other Side nothing to say for themselves? Has not <hi>Withrington,</hi> have not others answered, and that to the Satisfaction of Men of Conscience and Judgment? I am sure, he had the Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of both, few of his time being esteemed more for Learning; and One who having spent all his Life in Forreign Parts, had no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern in our Quarrels, said in my hearing, That <hi>Withrington</hi> had downright baffled two of the most Famous among all his Adversaries. Why, must all be dissembled, the ordinary <hi>Objections</hi> repeated as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, as if nothing were to be replyed, and no notice taken of any answer? People may carry it as they will; any Face may be set on any thing. But who will be medling in those matters, should do
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29438:4"/>well to remember, that Face will not always do it.</p>
            <p>Here is an <hi>Oath</hi> in the Case, an <hi>Oath</hi> which concerns our Duty to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Caesar;</hi> in which, if any be misguided, he is answerable to him, who misguides him. Tis not, or should not be, here as at the Bar, where a bad Cause too often finds an Advocate; one who whatever he thinks, speaks for his Client. People expect other deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from those who undertake to guide their Consciences; that they be truly Conscientious themselves, and who will not for Fear nor Favour, nor any Respect, make things better nor worse, nor other than just they are. Alas! How ill does he answer their Expectation who shews them but one side of the Medal? As much like Silver as it looks on that side, it may be arrant Brass; and he finds it so, who views it always. Of all counterfeit Coyn, counterfeit Truth is the worst, and the most damageable Cheat. It may purchase Credit and Applause: Right is not to be had, but for Truth. As it is of perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Consequence to be in the wrong in this Matter, let nothing be conceal'd, which conduces to judge whether we be or no. Let us not be possest with a vain Confidence of one Title. There is another set up: Let us fairly know what is in it. Let us have no cause to suspect, there is more concern that we should deal, than deal secure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; more concern for the Side, than the Truth. Both Sides lay claim to Her: Who truly desires the Cause should be right judged, will tell us what the <hi>Defendant</hi> says as well as the <hi>Plaintiff.</hi> A Guide of Conscience should desire nothing else. To be sollicitous only, that it may go on one side, is more for another Calling.</p>
            <p>In plain <hi>English,</hi> These half Lights are suspicious things; twenty to one, there are Bracks and Stains, where we must not see whether there be or no.</p>
            <p>And yet I would this were all, or the worst. Stubborn, ill-natur'd Arguments, which will not civilly be turn'd off, are, to say truth, very incommodious Duns. We should have some Indulgence, when People shift out of the way, or make as if they saw them not. 'Tis something less faulty, to conceal what others say, than to say our selves what is not true; or, if we will set up for Masters, what is weak. For a weak Argument, is a signe of an ignorant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, and 'tis unexcusable to pretend to teach what we understand not our selves. Too many Examples occur of both, but too often. To confine my self to my <hi>Letter;</hi> It is made up of Invectives, and Arguments; and there is not a jot of Strength in the One, nor Truth in the Other.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29438:4"/>
            <p> The <hi>Invectives,</hi> because they are strong at least, shall go first. Much pains he takes, and many words he spends, to make his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries ill thought of; as at a Design so charitable, who would stick out for pains? But yet, they are not the ill Men, he would have them pass for. Indeed they never set up for impeccable, that I know; nor ever thought the <hi>Oath</hi> an Antidote against Humane Frailty. This does draw some of them, as well as others, even from their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and he knows 'tis <hi>This,</hi> not the <hi>Oath,</hi> which does it. He meets of those who take it, at Mass still, and sees them stand to their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as constantly as their Neighbour-Refusers.</p>
            <p>For the rest, these Allegiance-Men, as luck is, live not in Deserts; they are to be found in the World, intermingled in the same Towns, sometimes the same Houses, with People of their own and other Religions, who know them, and their Dealings. Let these be ask't, Whether they deserve the Black Character of this <hi>Letter?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if he live not out of the World himself, with <hi>Ideas</hi> fram'd wholly by Guess, and unexperienc't Fancy; if he knows Men and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, 'tis strange if he be not acquainted with some of these People, whom he himself takes for honest Men, good Christians, good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and good Friends, and whom, upon occasion, he would trust as soon as other Folks, and as far. I will venture my Money, that this is so; and for all his big words, put it to his own Conscience. But whether he think well or ill of them, I doubt he has something to answer for. If ill, for having a bad Opinion of his Neighbour, who deserves it not: If well, for wronging them much, and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science more, against which he speaks.</p>
            <p>Then for his <hi>Arguments:</hi> I am strongly perswaded, there is not One, which he himself thinks will bear the Touch. He begins with One borrowed from the <hi>Third Treatise;</hi> which, as we have not always the care we should of what we borrow, is the worse for coming into his Hands. <hi>If the Supream Pastor</hi> (says he) <hi>is at any time to be obey'd, 'tis then when he commands in things appertaining to Faith and Salvation. But</hi> Popes <hi>have declared the Oath contains Matters contrary to Faith and Salvation.</hi> These two, perhaps, are not so well coupled; One making for <hi>Obedience,</hi> and the Other <hi>Belief.</hi> Bare Obedience, in matters of Faith and Salvation, may possibly be more questionable, than others. Because, where they are not concern'd, an unjust Command ought often to be obey'd; whereas no Command can oblige to the prejudice of Faith and Salvation. But as this will return again, I desire only to know at present, Whether
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29438:5"/>he thinks in his Conscience, that 'tis all one, to be contrary to Faith and Salvation, and to be declared to be so? Every Body, that has common Sense, every Body out of <hi>Bedlam</hi> knows, Things may be declared otherwise than they are, unless the Declarer be infallible. And this, indeed, he seems well content the <hi>Reader</hi> should believe of the <hi>Pope;</hi> for he gives him Magnificent Words. But I guess, by his falling presently off, he believes it not himself. However, he may take his Choyce. If he do not believe so, he speaks nothing to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; and must needs know, he does not. If he do, he does worse; for he brings in a new, and that uncertain Rule of Faith, and which leaves the Security of Salvation to the Mercy of a probable Opinion, if it be One. 'Tis much better to be talking nothing to purpose.</p>
            <p>Then he tells <hi>W. H. That the</hi> Pope, <hi>and a General Council are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, and have practised the Deposing Doctrine; and therefore, if that be erroneous, the Church is not Infallible.</hi> Does he in earnest believe this follows? Does he think the Churches Infallibility extends to Practises, other than what are warranted by Descent from <hi>Christ?</hi> Does not he, and all Christians know, the Promise of his Assistance was made with the Commission he gave, to teach what he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and that there is no Warrant to extend it farther? Do not we see, that Practises, even of Councils, have sometimes other Grounds, Discourses, and Speculations, not always necessarily true? If the <hi>Pope,</hi> and a General Council should happen to err in such things, why must the Church therefore forfeit her Infallibility? Time was, when the Bishops of one Nation thought they might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige their Prince, to lay his Crown at their Feet, and actually did. In all likelihood, the Bishops of other Nations thought their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er no less; and if they had met in a General Council, would have thought it lawful for all to do, what some had done. Does this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> for all that, think their Opinion true, or the Church the less Infallible, because it is not?</p>
            <p>Next, he keeps a Pother with <hi>Appealing,</hi> as he calls it, from the <hi>Pope</hi> to the <hi>Doctors of Sorbon.</hi> And he may use a Metaphor when he pleases; but, because he had it so often up, 'tis not amiss to observe by the way, that <hi>Appealing</hi> here signifies, barely asking the <hi>Doctors</hi> their Opinions. Does he, in earnest, think this so strange a thing? Does he think there ever was, or perhaps ever will be a Contest with the <hi>Pope,</hi> in which Divines have not, or will not be consulted? Or, does he think there must never be any Contest with him; but all he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, without more ado, be presently done, and all he says be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29438:5"/>For if there may be a doubt, whether in this, or that Case, People are obliged to believe or obey, he cannot think it so heinous a Matter to desire to satisfy that Doubt. If he know a better, or more unoffensive way, than to inquire, what unconcerned Men, good <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and good Schollers think on't, we are the less obliged to him, for making a Secret of it. Had he spoke in time, the mighty Mischief of saying to a private Man, <hi>Pray Sir what think you,</hi> might have been prevented. Indeed, if he will endure no Contest, no Doubt in any Case, (which he seems, as if he would fain be at, but speaks not out, for fear no Body should endure him) his Discourse is not inconsequent. 'Tis only abominably false, and abominably pernicious. In short, he may think he speaks Sense, if he can think with his Learned Quotations to make the <hi>Pope</hi> Infallible, and Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Doctrine a necessary Point of Faith. But 'tis but a moderate Glory, for which I would not betray the Church and Religion if I were as he.</p>
            <p>For his following Mirth, much good may it do him, and may it be hearty. For I have known People Laugh outwardly, who have been ill enough at ease within. Where lies the Ridiculous, and the Sham? <hi>Why, these Wise</hi> Doctors, <hi>when time was, subscrib'd to the Deposing of</hi> Henry <hi>the Third.</hi> As if it were not possible to pack an University, as well as a Jury; and as if it were not actually pack't at that Time, by the Power of the League. At least, so they say, who should best know, the <hi>French</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. But be as it will, He does not, sure, think the worse of the Subscribers for being of another Mind, than the Leaguers. <hi>I but</hi> Grandin, <hi>and his Fellow Readers Subscribed not, and this makes most be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Sham Subscription, or Sham Doctors.</hi> Is he in earnest trow, or does he jest on still? For methinks, 'tis pleasant enough to offer to perswade us that this Subscription is a Sham, and that by an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which bids fair to perswade us 'tis not. For what should hinder a Shammer from shamming in <hi>Grandin,</hi> as well as the rest? What should make him balk the Credit of a Chair, if there were no more in it, than to put in what Names he Pleased? But does our Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve one word of what he says? Does he truly think most Men, or any Men believes they did not Subscribe, whose Names we see; or are not what they pass for, <hi>Doctors?</hi> Why <hi>Grandin</hi> would not make one in so good Company, this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> if he would so fain know, may ask <hi>Grandin</hi> himself. If he think it was, because <hi>Grandin</hi> and the Subscribers are of different Sentiments in this Matter, he would
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29438:6"/>do well to get so much under <hi>Grandins</hi> hand. For I have been told, neither <hi>He,</hi> nor <hi>any,</hi> to whom the business was proposed, stuck out for that Reason. But every Body does not think himself obliged to say all he thinks true, at all times. 'Tis more a wonder, that the Love of barren Truth, which yields no Profit, should prevail on so many, as did Subscribe, then that some should think fit to think of something besides.</p>
            <p>But now he falls on with this potent Syllogism. <hi>If they who call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves Catholicks, have not faithfully observ'd every Material Point in the Oath, then are they perjur'd; but they have not observ'd every material Point: Ergo.</hi> As I have not heard People are obliged under Perjury, to spend their whole Stock of Observation upon Oaths, I should think this <hi>Gentleman</hi> might lawfully have kept some in reserve, to bestow upon his Arguments. A very little would have shewn him, that nothing he says is true. 'Tis not true, that his Adversaries have not observ'd every Material Point, and 'tis not true, that they are perjured, though they had not. Some other Sin, if it pleases him, instead of Perjury, Rashness, or Negligence, in the Concerns of the Soul, or what other Name the Case will bear; but no Perjury, till something be sworn, which the Swearer knows, or at least doubts is false. The Conscience must be violated, as well as Truth, by Perjury. Want of Fidelity, in making Observations, where one is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scious of it, is something another thing. But 'tis not true, that the <hi>Oath</hi>-Men are guilty even of so much. They do observe, and consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Material Point, in complement to those who put it in their Heads. For though it had never come there, I know not why it should be thought, that any thing material was left unobserved. The <hi>Oath</hi> has been faithfully enough observed, and critically scan'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most these Eighty Years. The Laws, and all manner of Treasons known; yet this Point in all this time, was never thought worth mentioning. Because some Body lately, either more lucky, or of more talent in finding Faults, has bethought himself to make a matter of it; must we, and our dull Ancestors, be Perjured, only for not being cunning in quick?</p>
            <p>The thing has indeed no difficulty, to any who will reflect that different things have often the same Names. <hi>You Swear,</hi> (says the Material Objection) <hi>to Discover all Treasons: Receiving Orders from</hi> Rome, <hi>is Treason by Law, and therefore are Perjur'd, if you discover not that among the rest.</hi> One might as well argue he were Perjured, who having sworn to bring into a Camp or Town, all the Horses, he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29438:6"/>could light upon, should leave behind the Horses on which wash-Maids dry their wet Linnen. Treason by Law, may be far enough from Treason in reality; And who will be content to grant me one modest request, to mend not only the sound of words, but take their sense along with him, will find in this Case it actually is so. For what does <hi>Treason</hi> by Law signify? Is it, that the Nature or notion of <hi>Treason</hi> is indeed found in receiving Orders from <hi>Rome,</hi> because the Law calls it <hi>Treason?</hi> Unless this be, there is barely the Name not the thing of <hi>Treason.</hi> Every thing has its Nature, which where it is not found, there is not that thing but another, with the same Name perhaps. So <hi>Treason</hi> is what it is; where that <hi>What</hi> is not, there is not <hi>Treason,</hi> nor can be, neither by the Power of Law, nor any thing else. Omnipotence it self cannot make things be What they are not. There remains then nothing that I see, for <hi>Treason</hi> by Law to signify, but that the Law punishes those who receive Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from <hi>Rome,</hi> as it does Traytors. So it often explains it self in this, and other Cases, of mere Legal <hi>Treason;</hi> saying, <hi>They shall suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, as in Case of Treason,</hi> or be reputed, or deemed, or adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Traytors,</hi> or the like. And if at any time it speak otherwise, it must also be so understood. For there is no Difference, save in sound, betwixt these two Expressions, <hi>This is, or shall be Treason;</hi> And, <hi>This shall be punisht as Treason.</hi> Whether the Law use the One, or the Other, what is meant can be no more than what is done. And the Law never does, nor can do any more, towards making <hi>Treason,</hi> what is not so of it self, but forbidding it under the same Penalty, and so giving or occasioning the same Name. Now <hi>punishable as Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> and <hi>Treason,</hi> having two very different Notions, a wonderful Material Observation it is, that they have both the same Name, and a mighty strong Argument to prove they are Perjured, who Swear to discover all <hi>Treasons,</hi> that they discover not quite another thing.</p>
            <p>If this were not so, <hi>Dun</hi> I can tell you, would be in the Mire as well as <hi>Ball.</hi> If the Swearer be Perjur'd, because he does not disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Priests, all that you, who Swear not, get by it, is, that you are a bad Man with another Name. For why do not you discover them, if they be indeed <hi>Traytors?</hi> Will a Yea, and Nay-Conscience, which allows not a Man to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> allow him to conceal a <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor?</hi> 'Tis a pleasant Conscience this of yours, if it perswade you that dispensing with one duty, giving the Prince security of Allegiance, is a sufficient ground to dispence with another, and suffering <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> to go undiscovered in his Dominions. You have no great mind,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29438:7"/>if one may guess by your writing, to have the <hi>Oath-men</hi> pass for bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Subjects then you; but yet you bid fair for it, if you would have it thought, they only are obliged to discover all <hi>Treasons,</hi> and you not. Swearing or not Swearing alters not the Case. Priests are, or are not <hi>Traytors,</hi> whether we Swear or no. You who say they are in vertue of the Law, must say too, That you are obliged to discover them. The Swearer, if you will, is more obliged, but to no more than you. For he is but obliged to discover all <hi>Treasons,</hi> and that he was before he Swore, and had been, though the Oath had never been thought of; and you are obliged to as much, unless you think the Law of Nature, and of <hi>God,</hi> besides the Law of the Land, oblige not without an Oath. For all this Obligation, there is nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Swearing. In short, if Priests be not Traytors, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be said to the Swearers; if they be, there is nothing to be said for the not Swearers. That nothing can make a Traytor of an honest Man, whether he will or no, is all the excuse of both; If that will not do, both are errant Knaves for ought I see, and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer only as Knight and Gentleman; one is a Sir Knave, a Villain with a Title, a Perjur'd Villain; the other but plain Knave, a Villain of low Degree, but a Villain too.</p>
            <p>And yet after all, 'tis true, that there is something Material in this Observation; so Material, that he was too blame, not to make a Secret of it, and keep it by all means from <hi>Protestants.</hi> For if they once get it by the end, and come to understand that <hi>Priests</hi> are <hi>Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> and to be discovered under pain of Perjury, what will become of poor <hi>Priests? Protestants</hi> all take the Oath, and some know of <hi>Priests,</hi> and say nothing, but have no mind, I suppose, to be damn'd for their sakes. For a small matter, Misprision of <hi>Treason,</hi> or so, <hi>Priests</hi> may count upon it. Who would refuse to venture Body and Goods for them, in a Country where they are so loved? But Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury too! why 'tis too much in all reason, One cannot fairly expect it. Your <hi>Informer,</hi> if this Doctrine be true, is the only honest Man of the Nation. Every Body, that knows of a <hi>Priest</hi> must out of pure Conscience set up of the Trade.</p>
            <p>The material Trifle deserves not so many words; yet now we are in, let us e'en see the last on't. A great absurdity the Author thinks it is, to say, That what is <hi>enacted</hi> by the Law to be <hi>Treason,</hi> is no <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi> To say, <hi>Legal Treason</hi> is not <hi>Legal Treason,</hi> were indeed some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing absurd. But may not a Man be in his Wits, who thinks <hi>Legal Treason,</hi> and <hi>Real Treason,</hi> go not always together? Do none but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29438:7"/>senseless Oath-men, think a <hi>Priest</hi> may be an honest Man, and the State run no extraordinary hazard, though he be never caught? <hi>Treason</hi> signifies a Crime, by which the Weal-publick is betray'd, and it signifies every thing punishable, with the punishment of that Crime. Is it any such Riddle, that the same thing should be <hi>Treason</hi> in One Sense, and not <hi>Treason</hi> in the Other? I but this is Equivocation, he says, and double Perjury. Equivocation is indeed Perjury in Oaths, as it is Lying in Speech. But if he will needs take a word Equivocal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, must we therefore be Perjured? Let every one bear his one Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, if he please. We understand the word <hi>Treason</hi> in the first, which we take to be the proper Sense, because we see, that all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, as soon as they hear of a Traytor, unless Circumstances sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest something else. have presently a horrid <hi>Idea</hi> in their Thoughts; something notably against the common Good either committed, or attempted; something abominably bad in it self, and which would be the same execrable Crime it is, though there were no Law about it. As <hi>Parracide</hi> was <hi>Parracide,</hi> and every jot as bad, where the Law forgot or forbore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o appoint it any punishment, as any where else. He would have us understand every thing which the Law calls by the same Name, and punishes with the same punishment. As if punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made or marr'd, or were any thing to the notion of the Crime punish't. <hi>Robbery</hi> and <hi>Murther</hi> are punisht alike, by our Law; yet they are very different things; and who should Swear to Discover One of them, would not be perjur'd by concealing the Other. And for the same Names, unless the same Notions go along with them, they leave the things as different as they were before. At this rate, one may possibly be a very honest Man, and an errant Traytor, at the same time. So <hi>Christians</hi> were all Traytors, or as bad, under the <hi>Heathens;</hi> and are still, it may be, both under <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Mahometans.</hi> In a word, his Notion is wholly Forreign, grounded on nothing found within the thing, but derived from something done about it from without, common Name and Punishment. And because we are a little dull, and apprehend not how the proper No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a thing should consist in external Considerations, sometimes applicable, and sometimes not; but fancy wildly, that things have proper Natures and Notions of their own, which remains the same whatever is done about them, we are Equivocators and Perjurers.</p>
            <p>Lastly, He dares be bound, the <hi>Judges</hi> shall give it for him. Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for his Bond, he must pardon us. Those are often most for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to be bound, who have least to pay.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:29438:8"/>
            <p> When we know what stock he has of Law, we will talk fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A Bond in a matter of knowledge, in which one has no skill, is like a Bond in a Mony-matter from one who has no Cash. Will he be bound, where he is a responsable Man? Bound to acquiesce in the decision of the Judges? bound to take the Oath, if they give it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him? For else, to trouble them to no purpose, is a Presump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of which I dare not be guilty; nor does he care what they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, nor is this the thing which sticks with him. But if he be in earnest, and will put it to reference, with all my heart. I'le not be out at any motion which promises an end of the quarrel. Let's leave disputing from this moment, and apply our selves to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. If their Goodness, which refuses no pains to end differences, will undertake the trouble, I engage for my self, and think I may for my Friends, to stand to their award, every jot as readily if it go against, as <hi>with</hi> me. For I am not fond of the Oath, though I love Allegiance. An End any way contents me. I am pretty confident though there is more of rash then stout in his daring. The Oath does not say, absolutely all Treasons, but all Treasons against the King. All Treasons are not such. It is Treason to kill the Chancellor, or some other Great Officers, it is Treason to Counterfeit his Coyn. The Law I suppose does not understand these to be Treasons against the <hi>King.</hi> Joyn Opportunity to Treason against him, and it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with his safety. He has been safe in the hands of a <hi>Priest,</hi> one who yet lives, and whom when the wisdom of the Nation thought fit to distinguish from his fellows, they took him not I sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose for one who meant any harm to the <hi>King.</hi> There is a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Statute to punish concealment of <hi>Priests,</hi> of which some have felt the smart: I never heard of one Indicted for Perjury on that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. All Men cry out a Traytor, as Fire in the Streets, upon the first appearance. He would be little better then a Traytor himself who should not. <hi>Protestants</hi> are not <hi>Heathens</hi> nor <hi>Athiests,</hi> but Men who know, what 'tis to forswear themselves. Divers know, or think they know, where there is a <hi>Priest</hi> and say nothing. No body for all that thinks them less honest Men then Informers, or less sollicitous of the <hi>Kings</hi> safety, or more indulgent to any Treason against him. I think then I have reason not to distrust a Tryal of this matter. One more, to say the Truth, I have, which in wary dealing perhaps I should not tell him, least he should fly back from his reference. But because he shall not say he was surprized, I will acquaint him, that I have taken his advice, and askt as he desired I should. And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29438:8"/>I am told that the words <hi>all Treasons</hi> in the Oath, are to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood of real Common-Law-Treasons, such as are indeed dangerous to the <hi>King,</hi> and reach not Nominal, and merely Statute-Treasons, and that this sense of the Oath is most evident. But yet as he may possibly distrust my word, and though I know I say true, chuse whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will believe me, I pretend not to conclude him by it. He is still free to go on with his reference if he think sit. One thing I am sure of, that hitherto there is no Perjury, no, though it should be as he says. Because who took the <hi>Oath,</hi> Swear uprightly according to their Conscience, understanding by Treasons true, not made Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and believing the <hi>Oath</hi> meant so; and I am confident there will be none hereafter, and that when it appears the Oath obliges <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks</hi> to deliver their <hi>Priests</hi> up to punishment, for no other fault then Priest-hood, none will take it more. And so I beg the Readers Pardon for detaining him so long on a Subject, which as material as this Gentleman makes it, I doubt after all is but much ado about no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>Scripture and Councils must be in too, else all had been marr'd. For what's an Author without a Quotation? without something to shew Reading, as the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>Brainford</hi> spoke <hi>French</hi> to shew breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? otherwise sure there needed no Councils to make Men confess, there has been such a thing in the World, as a Sentence of <hi>Depositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and that <hi>Sacro praesente Concilio</hi> too, in one, and but one Case. And there needed no Scripture, to perswade People that the <hi>Pope</hi> is as good a Man, as the High Priest was among the <hi>Jews,</hi> and has as much vertue in his Lips. For this is what he concludes from the <hi>One,</hi> and undertakes to prove by the <hi>Other.</hi> And yet, who can tell whether he had not a mind, his <hi>Reader</hi> should take <hi>Deposing Doctrine,</hi> for an Article of very Faith? For that People presently look for, when they hear of Scripture, and General Councils. One cannot easily judge, as he carries it, much as if he said, I will not tell you what I think my self; but would be glad, you would think it a Point of Faith. And Faith indeed made the great noise, at first, against the <hi>Oath;</hi> but who continues it still, have thought better of it since, and found it convenient to quit that Pretence, and say, 'tis not <hi>Faith.</hi> He, I suppose, for the credit of the common Cause, does not mean to fall out with his fellows, and say it is. For which reason, I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to say what the Occasion suggests, and as I take no Joy in disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering Faults, am well content that many I find here scape for me un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reproved and unobserved. Where Faith is not concern'd, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29438:9"/>it best to let Scripture and Councils alone.</p>
            <p>And as for the Oath, the Sport I think is at the best. We have seen either all, or the best he can, or at least thought fit to do. 'Tis not amiss now to cast an Eye upon what he performs against the Oath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. <hi>He does not find</hi> (he says) <hi>in all the Breves, that the</hi> Pope, <hi>either asserts his deposing Power, or commands any to assert it:</hi> All he requires, is a Civil <hi>Obedience from his Children in Spiritual Matters,</hi> things <hi>apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to Faith and Salvation.</hi> Now, <hi>if they will deny Obedience and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance (in such matters) to their Supreme Pastor;</hi> He <hi>cannot see, how possibly Princes</hi> can expect, <hi>or long hope for a Civil Obedience from such Subjects.</hi> And this is the only ground of all the Unkindness, with which he confutes his Adversaries.</p>
            <p>As I am something dull, I take not the jest. He, no doubt, can give an Account, how Obedience to a Spiritual Superior in Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Matters is civil Obedience; how Subjects come to owe Allegiance to any, but their own Prince, what 'tis to purpose, whether the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing Power be asserted in these <hi>Breves,</hi> if it be asserted elsewhere, and if we may believe him, in something stronger than a <hi>Brove;</hi> and what, besides not looking for it, hindred him from finding in the <hi>Breves,</hi> what others of his side have found; who tell us, the Denyal of Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Power is one of the many things asserted to be repugnant to Faith and Salvation. Which they make account is asserting the Power, as indeed it looks very like it. It might have gratify'd some Bodies Curiosity too I suppose, to have let them know, what he would have done, if he had found the Deposing Power asserted or commanded, in these <hi>Breves;</hi> or will do, when he finds it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>if a Breve</hi> be so material; obey, or Disobey? If Disobey o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers may hope his good leave to disobey a <hi>Breve,</hi> who would take it himself. If Obey, he thinks the Deposing Doctrine true, whether found in a <hi>Breve</hi> or no: For he would not, I presume, assert an Untruth for any Body's sake. He had e'ne as good declare himself, and assert it now. A Day or two sooner or later neither makes, nor marrs; and 'tis but a useless Nicety, to stand upon it.</p>
            <p>But of these, and the like matters, he may bethink himself at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure. 'Twill be time enough to make up his Accounts, when some Body calls for them. I concern my self only in his Jealousy of these, who take the <hi>Oath,</hi> and the ground he has to suspect them of Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to their Prince. 'Tis, I suppose, because who disobeys one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior, are like to disobey another. Yes truely, very like, in alike Age. Not to dissemble what is, there is no counting upon Obedience
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29438:9"/>from the Oathmen, whensoever, and by whomsoever they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, what they cannot with a safe Conscience obey. They have the grief to disobey the <hi>King,</hi> and his Laws once a Month; and once in their Lives, the <hi>Pope</hi> too: And cannot help it, while they are perswaded, <hi>God</hi> is to be prefer'd before Man, and that <hi>He</hi> requires they should do as they do. If they make bad use of a good Principle, and disobey where they ought to obey, there is something to be said to them: But if they do but what they ought, what he says is, in effect, they are guided by Conscience, and therefore not to be trusted; True to God, and therefore like not to be true to their Prince. Shew, if you please, that they do ill, in disobeying the <hi>Breves,</hi> before you run away with it into your long Carrier of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry <hi>Rhetorick. They Disobey</hi> (say you) <hi>their Supreme Pastor, Christs Vicegerent; Him whom</hi> God <hi>himself hath Commanded to Feed his Sheep, to Feed his Lambs,</hi> and to <hi>have care of his Souls.</hi> As if plain <hi>Pope</hi> were not as much as all this. They do disobey him, that's agreed. Why, is that disobedience blameable? And <hi>They dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey</hi> (say you) <hi>in things appertaining to Faith and Salvation.</hi> And what then? If it be not too unmannerly to ask a Question, where I know before hand there is no answer. But pray, which are these things, and where may we find them; in the <hi>Oath,</hi> or the <hi>Breves?</hi> In the <hi>Breves</hi> is only the Command, which is disobey'd. And they tell us too, that these matters are contain'd in the <hi>Oath.</hi> There we find Deposing Power deny'd, and Allegiance profest. These then are the matters in which the <hi>Pope</hi> is disobey'd. Pray, how come these to be Matters of Faith and Salvation? The Deposing Power indeed pretended as long as it could. But now even they, who oppose the <hi>Oath,</hi> have thought good it should pretend no longer. The other has reason to pretend, nothing in the Law of <hi>God</hi> being more express, then Duty to Princes. But no Body is unjust enough to imagine, the <hi>Breves</hi> ever thought of forbidding this Duty. It would be to forbid, what <hi>God</hi> commands; in which case he were no good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, who should doubt whom to obey. One may be subtle, in distinguishing betwixt <hi>Performance</hi> and <hi>Profession;</hi> say the latter is forbid, though the former be not. But this will have no pretence to a matter of Faith and Salvation. A wild Fancy it must needs be, into which it can enter, that the Law of <hi>God</hi> has left the Profession of Civil Allegiance in the Breast of Spiritual Power. And so most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently, for what concerns Allegiance, what can be said to be matter of Faith and Salvation, is not forbid; what can be said to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29438:10"/>be forbid, is not matter of Faith and Salvation. But this is but losing time for Methods sake. The <hi>Breves</hi> never meant to forbid Allegiance, or the Profession of it. Accidentally indeed they hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Profession which is in the <hi>Oath,</hi> because it is joyn'd with something, which they thought fit not to let pass, renouncing the Deposing Power. In truth, all rests upon <hi>That,</hi> and <hi>That</hi> being at last acknowledged to be no matter of Faith and Salvation, there remains no pretence for Disobedience in such matters.</p>
            <p>Though there did, there is something more to be thought of For what if such a Matter should happen to be determin'd wrong? What if we should be commanded to take Vice for Virtue, and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue for Vice. Must we, because these are Matters appertaining to Faith and Salvation, obey, and try to go to Heaven by the way of Vice? Must we learn a new Christianity? For the Old one teaches, that Virtue only leads thither, and Vice somewhither else. But let us understand one another. You who say, I must obey, because the matter appertains to Faith and Salvation, pray what do we mean? That the Matter commanded was revealed by <hi>Christ,</hi> and I must believe so, and testify my belief by my Obedience? Or, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided I obey, I may believe what I will? If you take it this latter way, I am beholding to your Indulgence for the liberty of setting my outward and inward Man together by the Ears, and making my Actions bely my thoughts. For where Faith is pretended for a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Obedience to it is, whatever I think in my Heart, a Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion that the Pretence is true. But your kindness will do me no good. Because, if the matter be revealed by <hi>Christ,</hi> I must needs believe it; and must not receive it into my Faith, if it be not revealed. I am obliged both ways, and 'tis not your leave which can discharge me. Besides that, how you can at the same time pretend a matter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to Faith, and allow every Body to believe it does not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s a Riddle which poses me. But if you will have my Belief go along with my Obedience, pray shew me why I must <hi>believe,</hi> before you tell me I must <hi>obey.</hi> For, you know, I must not entertain a wrong Faith for any Bodies sake, no not for an Angel of Heaven. Apply this to our Case. The <hi>Oath</hi> is forbid, because it contrives matters repugnant to Faith and Salvation; and this Prohibition, say you, I must obey, because it is in a matter appertaining to them. But if I obey, and believe the Repugnance mentioned, how shall I answer for that Belief? For making my self a Faith of my own, and receiving in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my <hi>Creed</hi> what neither I can find <hi>Christ</hi> ever revealed, nor any
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29438:10"/>Body else can shew me, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t said with the good leave of the <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chist.</hi> If I believe it not, now shall I answer for my Obedience? For owning by it, that a matter appertains to Faith, which I believe does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot? For perswading others, as far as my Example will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade, to believe what I believe not my self? Is it a slight matter to have a hand in confirming a wrong Faith in the World? Will your word bear me out? Pray permit me to think it is not here, as where we may, and ought obey; and at the same time below the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand perhaps unprofitable, perhaps prejudicial. Faith requires in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Assent, as well as outward Submission; make Faith the ground of a Command, I cannot see but that who believes there is a Faith to ground the Command, and yet obeys it, betrays Faith, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a Scandal to his Neighbour, whom he temps to believe <hi>Gods</hi> Law is other then it is, at least in his Judgment. And this, I suppose, they saw, who have attempted to make the <hi>Pope</hi> Infallible: He needs Infallibility no more than other Men, to oblige to a Conscientious Obedience; where right or wrong Obedience is due, as it often is, to all Superiors, though we think, and though we know the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand harmful. The Superior is to provide against that harm, when it appears to him, as well as other Folks, and his Subjects, to leave that care to him, and obey him. But every Subject is ans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werable for an Errour in Faith, as well as his Superior; every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy must look to his own Soul. And therefore, since Obedience to a Command concerning Faith, draws in Belief, either the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or must be exempted from Mistake, or the Subject from Obedience, when there is one. <hi>Bellarmin</hi> goes the first way; this <hi>Gentleman</hi> may follow him, if he pleases; and when he has made out that Point, urge Obedience freely. We, who believe, there is no Power, which can oblige us to believe amiss, take the Second, something the more confidently for his Argument. For what he brings, is not true, and if it were, ought to make us the more wary.</p>
            <p>So much harsh Descant upon such a ground! The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> importun'd with Suggestions of causeless Jealousy, for this! The <hi>Oath-men</hi> for this traduc'd, for men whom <hi>No Oaths will choke, who would stretch their Conscience to swear, for Worldly Interest; either what they know not, or what they believe not; and who, he is inclin'd to believe, break their Vows and Oaths, with as little concern, as you would a Rush!</hi> Papists <hi>in Masquerade! a kind of</hi> Janus-<hi>Fac't Monsters! Men who like</hi> Esau, <hi>will sell the Blessing of Heaven for a Dish of Pottage; and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der out</hi> God Dammes, <hi>and what you will, to save their Bacon! Men,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29438:11"/>who are ashamed of their Religion, and its Principles! Glory more in the Name than Thing! pawn their Faith, sell their Consciences <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ligion, betray the God of Eternal Truth and Life; and what know I?</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion upon no more occasion, from a side nicely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nder in this Point, and against which, if any thing come forth less smooth, or less kind; any thing, short of Love-letter; What Crys presently, what Peals of Uncharitable and Unchristian Ringing in our Ears? And yet, 'twere something, if he thought any of all this true. But he knows all this while, and sees with his Eyes, They save no Bacon, nor get no Pottage, nor have so much as a Prospect of Worldly Interest. Process for 20 <hi>s.</hi> a Month, or 2 Thirds goes out again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, as well as others. I would it did not. Perhaps they might be good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans then, very Conscientious Men, and of good Examples, and some Authority too, it may be. He knows too, they are not ashamed of their Religion, or its Principles; but are now again, in some Places, at the Mercy of their Old Sequestrators, for owning it. 'Tis the Deposing Principles, of which they are ashamed, and to see them pin'd upon Religion. This they see, with shame and Grief; but they blush not in this Case, for their own Faults. They sell not their Religion, or Conscience; nor can, while there is no Price paid. Some Wit in his Anger would have scrapt out this Objection, and put him in mind, that to part with a thing for nothing, is not to sell it.</p>
            <p>If he be indeed inclin'd to believe, they would break their Oaths so slightly, his Inclinations are worse than I can in Charity believe; though they are bad enough, if they have no ground but what he mentions; his Storm, and the <hi>Oath of Supremacy.</hi> People act not, but upon occasion; if he will call the Occasion they had to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> a <hi>Storm,</hi> must his Metaphor needs incline him to believe, they have no regard to an <hi>Oath?</hi> If he would do any thing towards allaying his Storm, 'twere more colourable to fancy some Relation between them; but as it is, his inclinations must e'ne trust to our Charity, for ought I see. Then the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> what business has that here? Or does he forget what he is talking of? When he is to tell us of Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Oaths,</hi> does he tell us of taking them? In short, his Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are absolutely groundless, and what they would carry him to believe absolutely false, for the <hi>Oath-men</hi> have that regard to <hi>Oaths,</hi> which the awe of Divinity requires! They do not strain their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences, nor do any of the ill things he mentions; and so, for all his Inclinations to the contrary, I verily think, he believes himself. As
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:29438:11"/>these are heavy Imputations, and which would stir even a patient Man, what if one should be revengful now? Does he think there is nothing to be retorted? Nothing in the Deposing Principles, which would furnish Matter to talk of the bad Subject, and the bad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science? He might chance to repent his Provocation, and find his Friends, who disown his Zeal, have reason. For no Jest bites like the true one; as he found by experience, who being askt, What ail'd him to be in such a mighty Passion? <hi>Why,</hi> (reply'd he) <hi>Yonders a Fellow has prefer'd a Charge of Villany against me; and the mischief is, the Rogue has proved it.</hi> But, as I find it much more sweet to benefit, then shame a Man, I only pray him for his own sake, to do better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother time, and either forbear to speak ill of other Folks, or at least say nothing but what he has some colour for, and what he thinks is true: And, if he be not too much to request at once, to acknowledge his Adversaries are not altogether the wicked Men, his <hi>Idea</hi> makes them, who can put up Injuries calmly; and so he is quit for me.</p>
            <p>The <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council</hi> are, methinks, or should be, above the Level of a Pamphlet. 'Twere good, in my Opinion, and no more than becomes the Respect due to them, to talk of something else. He may be one, for ought I can tell, that know him not, who may take upon him, and knows what he does, when he makes bold with them at every turn; and undertakes to instruct them, of whom they shall think well or ill. For us, I think 'tis but our Duty, to keep a greater distance; yet not to dissemble a just Ambition, we are, I confess, deeply Ambitious of their good Opinion; and make our Court, as we understand it, who come not there to learn. Live quietly, and privately, give them no trouble, if we can help it; and appear not before <hi>Them,</hi> till we are sent for: Which, if ever we be, I hope we shall have a wiser Story to tell, than to teach them, who are their Friends, and their Foes; and that they must beware of those, who Swear to be true to the <hi>King,</hi> who will sure enough stand by the <hi>Pope</hi> against Him in a Field, because they stand by Him, against the <hi>Pope,</hi> in an <hi>Oath.</hi> But the Men to bide upon are those of Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, who, the <hi>King</hi> may be sure, will always be true to Him, for this convincing Reason, because they will not Swear they ought.</p>
            <p>The next time he talks of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> he would do well to remember, that he speaks of the Wifest, to say nothing of their Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and most impartial Men of a great, and no stupid Nation. Who has a mind to impose upon them, should bethink himself of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29438:12"/>something more refined, than to say the <hi>King</hi> cannot expect his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects will obey Him, where they think, and swear they ought, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they obey not the <hi>Pope,</hi> where they think they ought not. Why? they disobey the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> only, because they fear to disobey the <hi>King;</hi> and <hi>God,</hi> who has commanded us to obey Him. To make that a ground to suspect their Obedience, is certainly the most pleasantly odd, among all the Fantastical Whimsies of causeless Jealousy.</p>
            <p>I must not forget the Imputation of <hi>Blackloism,</hi> it is so heynous a matter. <hi>Schism <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>Heretick,</hi> Unconsciencious and Irreligious, without <hi>Blacklois<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> had been nothing. He would have then the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty of the <hi>Oath-men</hi> suspected, beca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> some Sticklers for the <hi>Oath,</hi> admired <hi>Blacklo,</hi> and <hi>Blacklo</hi> taught Disloyal Doctrine. 'Tis well this suspicious <hi>Gentleman</hi> liv'd not in the Days of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> or St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> to suspect them of <hi>Heresy,</hi> because they admired <hi>Origen.</hi> If <hi>Blacklo</hi> taught Disloyalty, what would he have more of any body, than to leave him, and his Disloyalty to themselves; keep clear from the Infection, and preserve their Loyalty sound and untainted? And what better Proof would he have that they do this, than bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themselves in the strongest Bonds, of which humane Nature is capable, and endeavouring every body may do so too. He may as well suspect the Silver, which bears the <hi>Tower</hi> mark, as the Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which has been toucht by the Stone appointed by the Wisdom of the Nation. If other Folks should take example by him, and be suspicious too, what better Evidence can he bring of his own Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty? When he brings as much, his Suspicion will be more seasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; though 'twill shew but odly still, without a better ground, than admiring <hi>Blacklo.</hi> If they admire him for Disloyal Doctrine, if they abet him in it, 'tis something. But as long as they love Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty better then <hi>Blacklo,</hi> and stick to it, whatever he or any body says, they may admire till their Hearts ake, and be never the less Loyal. They admire <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> as well as <hi>Blacklo,</hi> but will not be Disloyal for either of their sakes. Make admiring <hi>Blacklo</hi> a ground of suspicion once, and there is not perhaps a knowing Man in the Nation to be trusted. As one may admire an Enemy; every Body, even of those who were most violent against <hi>Blacklo,</hi> thought him, for all that, a learned Man, (for that is the <hi>English</hi> of Admiring) this Gentleman I believe himself for company. Does he therefore think it just the Suspicion of Disloyalty, and abetting the bad Doctrine he mentions, should fall on himself, who yet cannot think worse of it, than the <hi>Oath-men.</hi> While there is not a Man on either side, who
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29438:12"/>holds that Doctrine, methinks we might be Friends for that matter Let the <hi>Blackloist</hi> be as bad as he will, the <hi>Oath-man</hi> is an honest Man. We think him not so bad, that one cannot be seen in his Company without Scandal, and find it more reasonable to think well of him for the <hi>Oath</hi> sake, than ill of the Oath for his. However it be, let him shift as he can for himself; our Business is with the <hi>Oath,</hi> not <hi>Blackloism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But after all, is it as this <hi>Gentleman</hi> says? For I know not how, with his Jealousie and Suspitions, he has put me into the distrustful Humour too. <hi>Blacklo,</hi> he says, taught, <hi>That we are bound to oppose a Banisht Prince, disputing with an Ʋsurper, to sight against, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him.</hi> Why, there is as much Ignorance, as Disloyalty, in this. He must be as much a Fool, as a Knave, who tells us, a Prince loses his Right, by losing a Battle. A Learned Man to teach this! Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple notwithstanding to admire his Learning, and his Integrity! Those who were bred up in so Disloyal a School, to prove Loyal, and Sticklers for Loyalty! This Tale does not tell. And I have nothing, but his Word for it; which, it may be, would have gone further, if he had not written. By his good favour, I mean to suspend my Judgment, till I can light on <hi>Blackloes</hi> Book. For 'tis but Justice, to hear both sides.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, There are Bayses in all Trades. <hi>Blackloism</hi> is one of the words they have got to express their <hi>no meaning</hi> by; a Twin to <hi>Jansenism</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> in <hi>England.</hi> No Signification belongs to any of the Three, but the Bayses use them, when they find a Man not for their turn, and have a mind to run him down, and nothing to alledge against him; For when they <hi>have,</hi> you never hear of these things. But when a Man gives no price, they cry out a <hi>Jansenist,</hi> or a <hi>Blackloist</hi> on him, who perhaps knows nothing of <hi>Jansenius</hi> or <hi>Blacklo;</hi> and <hi>Papist</hi> on him, who is at desiance with the <hi>Pope.</hi> By which they would have you apprehend some very bad thing, but which is not any one. A certain Sin, which is neither Pride nor Gluttony, nor any other; a Colour neither Black, nor Blew, nor Green; and so of all. Ask what this bad thing is, and wherein its particular Badness consists, and you spoyl all; you shall find either nothing at all, or nothing bad. As here; Admiring is no fault, at least, though there had been no cause, no great one: Holding Seditious Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is indeed a great Fault; but 'tis not committed. In a word, these Imputations are a sort of very bad Nothings. But yet they are convenient, because they may be in at every thing. Now, the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29438:13"/>
               <hi>Oath</hi> is naught, because <hi>Blackloists</hi> are for it; another time <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loists</hi> shall be naught, because they are for the <hi>Oath.</hi> The Trick will grow stale in time, and then every body will see what it is; and as soon as they hear of a <hi>Jansenist,</hi> a <hi>Blackloist,</hi> or <hi>Papist,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive presently it will, without a handsome Why. You may be sure, that so it always is; as sure as that the <hi>Protestant Papist</hi> is not the worst Protestant in the Nation; nor all Reprobates, who think not ill of <hi>Jansenius</hi> or <hi>Blacklo.</hi> And this I say not for any of their sakes, for I will not have to do with their Quarrels; but to shew what Arguments we have against the <hi>Oath.</hi> But the Pun of <hi>Black Doctrine</hi> was too smart to be lost, and so the Argument could not be spared.</p>
            <p>I have now done with this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and would fain hope the Difference of our Sentiments will not hinder me from obtaining a reasonable Request at his, and his Fellow Writers hands. 'Tis, That when they write next, they would consider a little more deeply, what they are doing, and what it is to set up for Masters and Guides. It is indeed a Charitable Office, of great both Praise and Merit; but it had need be well discharged. The Day will come, when an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count will be taken of it; where all the Acts, which serve in this World to support an ill grounded credit, and keep a Man from Shame, will go for nothing: Where there is no regard to a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterial out-fide; no minding who is decry'd, or cry'd up, nor by whom. Where the Grave look with a demurely confident Air, the Perswasive shrug, and Face of scornful pity, will not pass for Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Where nothing, in fine, will do it, but a clear Conscience. Far be it from me, to Question the Purity of any one; much farther to asperfe it. I only intreat every one, for their own sakes, to look to it, as the Concern requires, and see that all be right within. To ask themselves whither there be nothing in their Eye but Truth, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in their Heart but the love of it? No prospect of advantage or disadvantage some way, no Friend to please, or fear to displease? Whether they are themselves throughly perswaded, of what they would perswade others, and if they be, by what? Whether not as much or more by such motives, then any thing else? and whether their greatest reason be not, because they think it reasonable to do as they are bid? Every one has a Faithful Friend in his bosome, who will answer truly to these and the like Questions, and they are not their own Friends who ask them not. Our Souls are at Stake, and the credit of Religion. For what a prejudice, what a Scandal to a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:29438:13"/>Religion, to forbid those who are of it to profess their Allegiance, which to pay they are bound even by their Religion? Truth indeed is no just cause of Scandal; but they had need be very sure they say true, who say we may not profess our Allegiance, as he thinks fit we should, to whom we owe it. I cannot tell what to think, when I hear an honest Man say; I know not why it should be thus, and am sorry it is, but I am under Obedience; Time was, I told you, the <hi>Oath</hi> was lawful, and betwixt you and me, I think so still; but my Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors are wiser then I; I must not say so now. I wish all be well; but think it strange Language for good and Learned Men. Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a vertue; what makes us speak otherwise then we think, or think otherwise then reason directs, can be none. Because my Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior Commands me to take this or that side, must I therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude those who rely on me? They come not to ask what my Superior thinks or Commands, but what I think my self; and I must give them his Judgment instead of my own, and say, not what I would if I were at Liberty, but what he thinks fit I should; He who per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps understands not the business so well as I (for 'tis not Learning always which makes a Superior) or if he do, has the concern of his Order to look to as well as Truth, with all my Heart I Love and Honour the Obedience, which assists us to keep the Commands of <hi>God:</hi> But if any pretend to Oblige us to violate Truth and Sincerity, with all my Heart I pray for my self to be preserv'd from it, and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that it may be taken for an excuse when time comes. 'Twill prove but a sorry one, I doubt, even for those who can alledge it. What will become of the rest? and what will they have to say for their busy earnestness, their heat and their crys? 'Tis every Days talk; such a one is for the <hi>Oath;</hi> who would have thought it of him? I am sorry he has lost himself so; I wish him well; Pity he gives such bad Example. You who talk thus, do you know any thing of the matter? Can you Judge of the differences among Schollers? Does not your own Heart tell you, you have no reason for all this, but that some body said so; perhaps, no more knowing then your self; perhaps, in whom Obedience spoke more then Knowledge. Be sincere, if you please, tell the Story as it is; say, that some Body told you so; and let that Some-body answer for it. But make not your self responsible, for causing your Neighbour to be ill thought of, who if he do amiss, 'tis more than you can tell.</p>
            <p>Who are, indeed, perswaded the Truth is of their Side, should me thinks have a good Reason in store, why they are so perswaded,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29438:14"/>and bring it out when 'tis call'd for, or they voluntarily undertake to perswade others. Something of more Appearance, at least, than what we find here, and generally elsewhere. It should not suppose the Question, instead of proving it. As here, where the Question is, Whether we are bound to obey these <hi>Breves</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> or no; and the proof, we are bound to obey our Supream Pastor, in things ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to Faith and Salvation? As for supposing, that ours are such matters, let that pass: To ask, whether we are to obey the <hi>Breves;</hi> is it to ask, whether we are to obey in the Matters Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the <hi>Breves;</hi> that is in the Matters of Faith and Salvation, if they be so. Again, because the same Man may be a Superior in one Matter, or one Respect; and Inferior in another, to ask, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Superior may be disobey'd, is to ask whether he may be diso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd in Matters wherein he is a Superior. For in what he is not, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience cannot be due to him. The <hi>Pope</hi> now being a Superior in Matters of Faith and Salvation, to ask whether he may be disobey'd, is to ask whether he may be disobey'd in such Matters. When for Proof then, that we must obey in such Matters, we are told we must obey in such Matters; we have no more, but barely the thing sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, of which we inquire; no more than just, we must because because we must.</p>
            <p>Some Honesty too would do well in a Reason, as well as a Servant. Disputes thrive as ill as Families, when we employ unfaithful Agents, and who are not true to the Cause; Mercinary Gentlemen, ready to take pay on the other side, as soon as they can get Entertainment. What He employs, to set us ill with the <hi>King,</hi> we thank him; would fly in his Face, and do as much to set him ill with the <hi>Pope,</hi> barely forbidding. 'Tis but putting, by the Rule of Transposition, Spiritual for Temporal, and saying to the <hi>Pope:</hi> Promise your self no Obedience from one that disobeys his own Prince, in a Matter most belonging to a Prince, Allegiance; He will never be true to You in Spirituals, who fails his own Prince in Temporals. Flourish this a little after his Copy, with <hi>Gods</hi> Vicegerent, whom we are to obey, <hi>not only for Wrath, but Conscience;</hi> who is set over us for praise of the Good, and Terrour of the Bad; who bears not the Sword in vain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Auxiliary is as trim, and as stout against Him and Us. Set him upon doing you the same ill Office with the <hi>King,</hi> which you would do us, and he is for you there too. 'Tis easily said, such a one disobeys in one thing, trust him not in another. Such Arguments are a kind <hi>Bravos,</hi> in the Common-wealth of Learning;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29438:14"/>as ready, and as willing for their hire to cut his Throat, who bid them kill, as his whom they kill'd. And the Mischief is they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways at hand; no body can miss one, who will look for him. But then then they are not fatal. One may live, when they have done their worst.</p>
            <p>The Reason too, in fair dealing, which you would have mine, should be yours. Pretences will never be wanting; but a Reason and a Pretence, are two things. He who after what he brings for a Reason is found faulty, continues as much sixt to his Tenet as before, has I am sure something else to six him, and only trys an experiment: Which where it succeeds there is so much got; where it fails, 'tis but a Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logism lost. Let us have <hi>bona fide</hi>-doings; the Concern deserves it. Propose to us, if you would have us of the mind, the very Motive which makes you be of it, that for which you indeed think the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine true, and which if it held not, you will be content to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Reason is not on the side. The Deposing Power, and the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical were more <hi>A-la-mode</hi> at first; Disobedience and Treason are most talkt of now. Chuse of these, if these be the true Reasons, or any other which you think the strongest, that on which you rely your self. Some convincing Reason you have, or you are either not convinc'd, or not rationally: And One will do it, as well as a Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Pitch upon the One, which you think will do; but stand by it; and as it proves, so let the Cause go. To start <hi>now</hi> one thing, <hi>then</hi> another, and another, and back again, and over and over again, is to say: I must make a Shew; you shall take these for the Reasons, if you please, which likes you best: I'le not be bound up by any of them. What Reason I have for my self, is another matter: These are what I thought most convenient to offer to you. In short, If you do not produce the true Reason, all you say is pure Pretence; and till we can hear of something, of which you will say, These shall end it, answer me this and I have done: How can we think we have the true Reason, any more than Colour, to maintain the Side without losing the Credit? But which you maintain not for its sake, nor value more perhaps than other Folks.</p>
            <p>Dally thus a while longer, and People will be apt to suspect 'tis In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treague all, and pure Cabal. So many Schollars, as are now leaug'd against the <hi>Oath,</hi> to agree in this point of Schollarship; upon pure Conviction of Reason, whom no Reason, yet invented by Man, could e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring to agree in any other: Faith and Authority left by <hi>Christ,</hi> in every bodies Mouth, and your Writings acknowledging that the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29438:15"/>point belongs not to Faith, and you Hearers bearing you Witness, that all the Authority in Question, is an Authority to settle a Doctrine never taught by <hi>Christ;</hi> and besides, with your good Favours, false and prejudicial both to Government and Religion: Cause shewn, why your claim should be over-ruled, that Cause supprest, and the claim as considently urged, as if there were nothing against it: These and the like sound suspiciously. Then we see the side you take, pleases where these, on whom you depend, live and desire to please; As who has pretences in a Court, must needs strive to be well with the Prince. It pleases there, if that be to purpose; because 'tis thought true, and beneficial to the World, as a bridle to Vice. And 'tis thought true, because in a Nation, where <hi>Tramentano</hi> is but another word for Fool, nothing is valued in comparison of their own Divines, and they unluckily happen to be in the wrong. However it be, we see your Superiours have Influence on you, and the <hi>Pope</hi> on them. We see this Influence may combine you more then Reason, perhaps can, at least does, if that be your Reason which you offer us. For that may be seen through, without Spectacles. Though this should work with you, we see you have no great Reason to propose it to us; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we should perhaps not think a thing the truer or falser, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more or less agreeable to your Interests. Whether it does or no, your own Hearts can best tell; into which I take not upon me to enter. But as we live in a mistrustful Age, let not the Suspicion take root, if I may advise you. Zealous we, who think we do migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Matters for Faith, and the Authority of <hi>Christ</hi>'s Vicar, by doing all we can against the <hi>Oath,</hi> may come to say one day; What, am I with my Zeal, and busie Concern, only serving all the while, it may be the Interest, it may be the Passion of other Men? Labouring that the Divines of <hi>Rome</hi> may get the better, and pass for abler Men in the World, than the Divines of <hi>France?</hi> That some Body may be better look't on at <hi>Rome,</hi> than some Body, and stand fairer for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences? That there be Examples of the Desert of some Members, to attone for Distaste taken at others? Must I be his Implement, who thinks he has found the Secret of maintaining the Deposing Power, without appearing for it, the Address to get the Merit, and decline the Envy? I, who believe it not my self, as those very few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Laity, even of those who refuse the <hi>Oath,</hi> who do? Must I think there are no good Christians, but those who believe <hi>Christ</hi> has left a Power to establish false Doctrine, and obey it when it does? When it comes to this, you must come out with your true Reason;
<pb facs="tcp:29438:15"/>and that Reason be such, as will satisfie a Reasonable Man. 'Tis ill putting off things to the last; you had as good do it now.</p>
            <p>And so the <hi>Reader</hi> is quit of me. However he find my Discourse, I hope he will not find my Pretensions unreasonable. No Body would be the worse, who should grant me all I desire; that the Love of Truth may be as much in our Hearts, as Mouths; and that, as we are aware, 'tis shameful not to say, I am concern'd for nothing else, and I have her on my side; we would remember, 'tis a great deal more shameful not to say so sincerely. You who say you have the Truth, have some Marks sure, by which you know her. By which of any yet assigned, can any body else know the <hi>Oath</hi> is naught? By <hi>Priestly Treason?</hi> Why then was the <hi>Oath</hi> opposed, when that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought of? By <hi>Deposing Power?</hi> Why then is it opposed still, when that is waved? Can either be the Cause of a Feavor; which abates not, when they are removed? No one can perhaps be pitch'd upon, of which it will not be said, the <hi>Oath</hi> might do well enough, if that were all. But this is the Business, says one; that, says ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Bidding fair to make other Folks think, that opposing the <hi>Oath,</hi> in which they all agree, is the only business of all, besides ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving something to say. And this something every Body sees; but whether any Body, besides themselves, sees the very motive they have to oppose the <hi>Oath,</hi> is a Doubt, which I think they would O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blige the World to resolve. Then, How many are eager against the <hi>Oath,</hi> who never saw it, or if they did by Chance, or Curiosity, will not examine it, nor hearken to any thing alledged for it. Never so little Scrupulosity, would make them shy to hazard injuring their Neighbour, and their Prince; having a hand in propagating false and pernicious Doctrine, scandalling Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And yet their Zeal may be doing this all the while, for ought they can tell. Though there were no other World, and no Account to be made in it, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it shews altogether as handsome in this, to talk of what they do understand, as to refuse to understand what they will talk of. Why People should distrust themselves, I know not. There is no Witchery in this business. But who will not, or think they cannot understand it, can let it alone, if they please. To say, I am sure the <hi>Oath</hi> is a very bad thing, and they very bad Men who are for it, but I do and will know nothing of either, seems to me a Tale which may be left untold, without prejudice to any Body. In fine, I am unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable enough, to wish with all my Heart, that no suspicion may
<pb facs="tcp:29438:16"/>remain of ungrounded Animosity, and blind Earnestness, of Partiality or Prejudice, that there may be an End made of a vexatious Dispute, and ways taken, by which we may at last hope to come to it. And I am uncharitable enough, to seduce others, if I can, into the same irrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal and uncharitable Perswasions. For the rest, some I believe will think I have said <hi>too much,</hi> and some <hi>too little.</hi> As indeed an <hi>Answer</hi> would have askt <hi>more,</hi> and <hi>fewer</hi> Examples perhaps have serv'd. I intreat the <hi>One</hi> to remember I disclaim'd Answering at first, and the <hi>Other,</hi> that t'other Argument tempts like t'other Bottle. While so much remains equally provoking and easy, I for my part think it something to break off where I do.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>